<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[CodePath]]></title>
  <link href="http://codepath.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codepath.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-24T00:28:20-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://codepath.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[CodePath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dark Patterns]]></title>
    <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/23/dark-patterns/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-23T19:26:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/23/dark-patterns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>UX involves having an understanding on the user&#8217;s behavior and influencing it, watching them while they use an interface and reacting to that. Where&#8217;s the line between influence and manipulation in design?</p>

<p>As with any other tools we can use interaction design honestly and deceitfully. Every heuristic and pattern has two sides, so it&#8217;s up to you wether to be on the dark side of the force or not.</p>

<h2>What&#8217;s a dark pattern?</h2>

<blockquote><p>Dark Patterns are not mistakes, they are carefully crafted with a solid understanding of human psychology, and they do not have the user&#8217;s interests in mind.</p><footer><strong>Harry Brignull</strong> <cite><a href='http://wiki.darkpatterns.org/'>darkpatterns.org</a></cite></footer></blockquote>


<h2>Shared knowledge = no cheating</h2>

<p>These dark patterns as well as persuasion techniques are only useful when the victim doesn&#8217;t know about them.</p>

<p>If we know what we are dealing with it&#8217;s less likely that we fall for them. Here are some examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://wiki.darkpatterns.org/Sneak_into_Basket">Sneak into basket</a>:
Suggesting related products on the checkout is fine, but adding them straight on your cart is a whole different story. Users need to <em>remove the items</em> them if they manage to notice them in the first place.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://wiki.darkpatterns.org/Roach_Motel">Roach Motel</a>:
Making it really easy to perform certain actions (sign up, buy, subscribe) and then extremely difficult to revert those actions. Making this hard can consist of burying that feature under several layers of navigation, or plainly not providing a way to do that online.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://wiki.darkpatterns.org/Forced_Continuity">Forced Continuity</a>:
Forcing users to provide credit card information to sign up for a &#8220;free trial&#8221;. Then, after the trial period is over the user automatically starts getting billed without any notifications.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://wiki.darkpatterns.org/Trick_Questions">Trick questions</a>:
Asking ambiguous questions, which when glanced upon appear to ask one thing, but if read carefully, asks another thing entirely.</p></li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<h2>Can&#8217;t see the forest for the trees?</h2>

<p>Focusing just on conversion rates and not on the customer&#8217;s feelings can cause great damage.</p>

<p>With the rise of the lean startup movement we feel in the need to reach high conversion rates in very short periods of time. We implement one design solution after another, everything is run on metrics, so some people might think that A/B testing has always the the final answer, however, sometimes we need to take a step back and analyze where we stand.</p>

<p><strong>A conversion is only meaningful when honestly achieved and really intended by the user.</strong></p>

<p>If users feel deceived they might end up hating your company and publicly complaining to let others know about the scam. This can cause great damage on a brand&#8217;s image and it&#8217;s not efficient in the long run. In fact, there are several persuasion techniques that can be applied effectively without causing that resent feeling in the users.</p>

<h2>There&#8217;s no such thing as neutral user interfaces</h2>

<p>We are always sort of directing the user&#8217;s behavior, and to work in an interdisciplinary team we should definitely let marketers do their jobs. Here are some persuasion techniques presented by Robert Cialdini on his book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Influence-Psychology-Persuasion-Business-Essentials/dp/006124189X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1300903223&amp;sr=8-1">&#8220;Influence: The Psychology of Persuasion&#8221;</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reciprocation:</strong> We want to return favors granted to us. If we feel that an app or website has done something for us, it&#8217;s more likely that we want to return that favor by donating, sharing or whatever favor is asked to us.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Commitment and consistency:</strong> We want to be consistent with our sayings
If we&#8217;ve posted on Facebook that we like company X, we&#8217;ve identified ourselves with that, so it&#8217;s more likely that we want to stick with that on the future.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Social Proof:</strong> We enjoy doing what others do.
This is a really wide-spread technique, you may have seen it as the &#8220;Popular choice&#8221; on a price comparison table or drop-down. Even when it&#8217;s just in the form of an already selected radio button, default options are huge decision facilitators, so we should use them wisely with clear wording so the user is in control.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This principle also takes the form of activity streams and successfully engages users to interact with applications.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Liking:</strong> We tend to comply more if the requester is someone we know and like.
That&#8217;s why referrals are for: &#8216;Share this referral link and both you and your friend will get $5 on credit&#8217;,
&#8216;John invites you to join XXX app on Facebook&#8217;, &#8216;Peter has sent you a DropBox invite&#8217;.</li>
</ul>


<p>As long as the user agrees on sending this communications this can be a powerful tool.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Authority:</strong> If a credible source says so, then we are in.
We&#8217;ve seen this every time a sites uses an SSL badge, or some kind of certification. Users feel safer if a well known institution has certified the site or app they are interacting with. This technique is the basics of advertising where public figures represent a certain brand or site to give it more credibility.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Scarcity:</strong> We want to act fast if the resource is limited.
An honest use of this technique would be to inform about the remaining stock of a certain product on an e-commerce site. A deceitful use would be to alter that data in order to create a sense of emergency when there&#8217;s actually plenty of stock.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>As you can see design patterns as well as persuasion techniques can be used both for good and evil, so where&#8217;s the line between them?</strong></p>

<h2>Expectation Management</h2>

<p>In my humble opinion a balance between the interests of the users and the company can be achieved with proper Expectation Management.Users should always be in control and know exactly what to expect from any interaction with our site our app.</p>

<p>With resources such as <a href="http://wiki.darkpatterns.org">darkpatterns.org</a> the design community is getting stronger by creating a simple way to say no when we are asked to do unethical work.</p>

<p>Empowering a more balanced mindset where quantitative data is as important as qualitative data is crucial for any company to last. Credibility and trust on a company are the basics to achieve customer loyalty.</p>

<p>After all&#8230; if you felt cheated. Would you come back for more?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enter the dojo: Deferreds and promises]]></title>
    <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/18/enter-the-dojo-deferreds-and-promises/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T17:23:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/18/enter-the-dojo-deferreds-and-promises</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&#8217;ve been working with javascript long enough, you probably have
faced a very common asynchronous programming challenge many times:
<em>Having to execute code after an asynchronous task finishes</em>.</p>

<p>A common solution is to use <em>callbacks</em>, just passing one or more
functions to the asynchronous task so it can call them when the result
is available. Unfortunately as the problems get more complex, like
having different callbacks for handling success/error results, nested
async tasks (and callbacks), tracking progress, communication between
callbacks themselves or all of them together things start to get ugly,
code usually becomes much harder to maintain, errors are harder to
handle, etc&#8230;</p>

<p>In fact this problem is so common in the javascript world that
<a href="https://github.com/joyent/node/wiki/modules#wiki-async-flow" title="Control flow/async modules">many implemented solutions</a> exist and a lot  those use promises
or other similar concepts.</p>

<p><strong>Promises are a simple solution found in many concurrent languages
that provide an effective and efficient way for handling and compose
concurrent tasks</strong>.</p>

<p>The idea is that instead of having the main task passing the callback
to the async task so it can then call it, responsibilities are
flipped: the async task creates and returns a promise (a proxy object)
that allows the main task to bind one or many callbacks. These
callbacks will be automatically executed when the result of the async
task is available.</p>

<p>This approach has many advantages over good ol&#8217; callbacks, I&#8217;ll try to
elaborate on this here while introducing dojo promises implementation
(v1.8). Note that most of what&#8217;s discussed here applies to other
implementations, specially the ones that follow
<a href="http://wiki.commonjs.org/wiki/Promises/A" title="CommonJS Promises/A">Promises/A CommonJS proposal</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Dojo Deferreds basics</h2>

<p>In the dojo toolkit the <em>dojo/Deferred</em> module defines the <em>Deferred</em>
class which along other modules in <em>dojo/promises</em> allow communication
between async tasks using the promises concept. Many dojo modules rely
on deferreds for their async communication, probably the best example
is the <em>dojo/request</em> module it can be used by your own modules as
well.</p>

<p>Code first, a simple example to demonstrate how you can create a
Deferred object in a async process and return a promise to the
consumer, who will be able to add a callback which will be executed
when the promise is resolved (and the result becomes available).</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px"
        src="http://jsfiddle.net/gonz/2R3Af/embedded/js,html,result/"
        allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>A Deferred object can be in one of three states at any given time:
<em>in progress</em> (or unfulfilled), <em>resolved</em> or <em>rejected</em>. It can only
go from <em>in progress</em> to <em>resolved</em> or from <em>in progress</em> to
<em>rejected</em>. This method allow us to make these status transitions:</p>

<ul>
<li><em><strong>resolve</strong>(value, strict)</em>: This method will be called to inform
the deferred that the async task finished successfully, this will
fire all the success callbacks added to it&#8217;s promises through the
<em>then()</em> method.

<ul>
<li><em>value</em> usually holds a result from the async tasks which will be
passed to the first callback as it param.</li>
<li><em>strict</em> is a boolean, when set to true makes the call raise
an exception if the deferred is already fulfilled. Defaults to
<em>false</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em><strong>reject</strong>(value, strict)</em>: Will be called when the async process
had some kind of error, all error callbacks functions will be
called. <em>value</em> and <em>strict</em> params work like the ones described for
<em>resolve()</em> above.</li>
</ul>


<p>You can check the current status of a deferred (or it promises) by
calling isResolved(), isRejected(), isFulfilled().</p>

<p>As can see in the example above <em>runAsync()</em> function returns the
<em>promise</em> attribute of the <em>Deferred</em> object, this is a
<em>dojo/promises/Promise</em> object that shares the <em>then()</em> method (and
it&#8217;s context) with the deferred, so when adding new callbacks through
the promise they will be available for the main deferred object
to call.</p>

<p>As you can guess <em>then()</em> is how we add callbacks with the code we
want to be run once the deferred is fulfilled.</p>

<ul>
<li><em><strong>then</strong>(callback, errback, progback)</em>: Add callbacks to

<ul>
<li><em>callback</em> is a function that will be called when the deferred is
resolved (finishes successfully).</li>
<li><em>errback</em> is an optional function that will be called when the
deferred is rejected.</li>
<li><em>progback</em> is an optional function will be called when the deferred
receives a progress update.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Chaining <em>then()</em> calls</h2>

<p><em>then()</em> returns a new <em>Promise</em>, so you can easily chain many <em>then()</em>g
calls or pass the promise to other contexts which may add their own
callbacks (and this detail is key for understanding the power of
promises).</p>

<p>An important detail here is that the callback added first (whether is
a sucess, error or progress callback) will get the result sent by the
<em>resolve()</em>/<em>reject()</em>/<em>progress()</em> call as its first param, the
return value of a callbacks is what the next callback in the <em>then()</em>
chain will recieve as first param, allowing callbacks modify or extend
it, as a simple uni-directional simple communication system between them.</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px"
        src="http://jsfiddle.net/gonz/7JdjB/embedded/js,html,result/"
        allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<h2>Progress updates</h2>

<p>A great feature of dojo&#8217;s deferreds/promises are progress callbacks,
They allow the consumer code to get progress updates from the async
process.</p>

<p><em>Deferred</em> defines the progress() method, which will call all
progback functions added using then():</p>

<ul>
<li><em><strong>progress</strong>(value, strict)</em>

<ul>
<li><em>update</em> is passed along to the progress callbacks added through
<em>then()</em>.</li>
<li><em>strict</em> works like <em>resolve()</em> and <em>reject()</em> methods strict param.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Take a look at this simple but cool example that make use of this feature:</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px"
        src="http://jsfiddle.net/gonz/g7ELP/embedded/js,html,result/"
        allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<h2>Cancelling async processes</h2>

<p>You can also cancel a deferred from the consumer side by calling the
<em>cancel()</em> method on a <em>Promise</em> object. Note that cancelling
behaviour has to be implemented on the deferred since it doesn&#8217;t
always makes sense to support that.</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px"
        src="http://jsfiddle.net/gonz/TNZHd/embedded/js,html,result/"
        allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>As you can see in this example the cancel behaviour for the deferred
is implemented passing a function to the <em>Deferred</em> constructor
function, and later called after the <em>cancel()</em> call in the consumer
side <em>Promise</em> object.</p>

<h2>Composing promises</h2>

<p>Dojo also provide two very useful modules for composing promises:
<em>dojo/promises/all</em> and <em>dojo/promises/first</em>.</p>

<p><em>dojo/promises/all</em> receives multiple promises and returns a new
promise that will become fullfilled once all of the given promises are
fullfilled.</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px"
        src="http://jsfiddle.net/gonz/65hdt/embedded/js,html,result/"
        allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>As you can see in the example the promise created by <em>all()</em> recieves
as first param an array of the results ordered in the same order we
passed the original promises. Alternatively you could pass it an
object using some keys to identify each value promise, the <em>then()</em>
callback would also recieve an object with the results in
corresponding key.</p>

<p>Similarly <em>dojo/promises/first</em> takes many promises and returns a new
promise that will become resolved as soon as any of the orginal promises
gets resolved.</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px"
        src="http://jsfiddle.net/gonz/VhESK/embedded/js,html,result/"
        allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<h2>Why promises are better?</h2>

<p><em>Promises</em> are an awesome solution for many reasons, for me the main
ones are:</p>

<h3>Simple APIs</h3>

<p>Not having to pollute function signatures with callback params allows
to have cleaner and intuitive APIs, just saying this method returns a
promise is enough.</p>

<p>If you have used libraries like jQuery I bet you had to go back to the
docs more than once to check async functions signatures, is the success
callback is the first or second param? What key does the param object
param expects? was it &#8220;complete&#8221;, &#8220;onComplete&#8221;, &#8220;success&#8221;?.</p>

<h3>Modular</h3>

<p>From the consumer perspective this approach makes things much flexible,
you can create as many callbacks as you want and compose them as you
see fit.</p>

<p>You can pass promises around your modules where each can add callbacks
or query the current status of the promise in a modular way, without
affecting the original deferred.</p>

<p>From the &#8220;async&#8221; side you don&#8217;t have to think about how to call the
callback, it&#8217;s just a matter of create the promise and manage it&#8217;s
states, what happens then is not it&#8217;s business.</p>

<h3>Composable</h3>

<p>As you saw above you can compose promises in useful ways and the
resulting code is very clean and intuitive. <em>then()</em> chaining,
<em>all()</em> and <em>first()</em> are great examples, and you can also easily
define your own logic to get a new promise from other(s).</p>

<p>With <em>callbacks</em> solution defining several serial callbacks it&#8217;s a
mess, I have seen those awfully nested functions too many times, of
course you can arrange the code to avoid nesting things too much but
the complexity to follow the code is the same: too high and the worst
thing: each function is responsible to call the next. With promises
you just would chain <em>then()</em> calls each function doesn&#8217;t know
anything about the others.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.8/dojo/promise/Promise.html" title="dojo/promise/Promise reference">dojo/promise/Promise reference</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.8/dojo/Deferred.html" title="dojo/Deferred reference">dojo/Deferred reference</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.8/dojo/promise/all.html" title="dojo/promise/all reference">dojo/promise/all reference</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.8/dojo/promise/first.html" title="dojo/promise/all reference">dojo/promise/all reference</a></li>
<li><a href="http://wiki.commonjs.org/wiki/Promises/A" title="CommonJS Promises/A">CommonJS Promises/A</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/joyent/node/wiki/modules#wiki-async-flow" title="Control flow/async modules">Control flow/async modules</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/domenicdenicola/callbacks-promises-and-coroutines-oh-my-the-evolution-of-asynchronicity-in-javascript" title="Callbacks, Promises, and Coroutines (oh my!): Asynchronous Programming Patterns in JavaScript">Callbacks, Promises, and Coroutines (oh my!): Asynchronous Programming Patterns in JavaScript</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An introduction to Lean UX]]></title>
    <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/17/an-introduction-to-lean-ux/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-17T13:15:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/17/an-introduction-to-lean-ux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://codepath.io/images/lean-ux/lean-agile-traditional.png"></p>

<p>There&#8217;s been a lot of buzz around Lean UX this year. Their critics, who call it Lazy UX, state it ignores the insights that only research provides. Those who like it, call it an UX evolution, a faster process that adapts to rapid changing market needs.</p>

<p>To define what Lean UX really is we should focus on what has been left out from Traditional UX. Never changing goals are something hard to picture on a startup. Avoiding time consuming documentation in favor of a greater focus in real life metrics is key in Lean UX.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In traditional UX, research is something we make before the product is conceived, in Lean UX research is not just a step that gets done before or after the product development. Instead, the UX team is constantly defining user needs based on user behavior.</p>

<blockquote><p>The prototype now becomes your documentation. It is &#8216;the Spec.&#8217; Very little if anything more is needed</p><footer><strong>Jeff Gothelf</strong> <cite><a href='http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2011/03/07/lean-ux-getting-out-of-the-deliverables-business/'>Smashing Magazine</a></cite></footer></blockquote>




<figure>
  <img src="http://codepath.io/images/lean-ux/process_graphic.gif" title="'Credits: Jeff Gothelf'" >
  <figcaption>Credits: Jess Gothelf</figcaption>
</figure>


<p>When you focus on the experience itself and not on documentation you can speed up the process of prototyping your concept, validating it and learn from user experience. An already known process if you&#8217;re familiar with Agile methodology. Tools like A/B testing are a great help when you need to test multiple concepts with your users.</p>

<p>Lean UX is a perfect fit for the lean startup movement, regardless of your team&#8217;s methodology of choice.
On the startup environment it&#8217;s crucial for teams to be constantly analyzing both the marketplace, and the product itself as pivoting in time can determine the success of the whole operation.</p>

<p>IMHO Lean UX won&#8217;t replace traditional UX, however, it is definitely an interesting alternative for those who do not have a lot of resources available and need to validate their product/market quickly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby on Redis]]></title>
    <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/2012/08/27/ruby-on-redis/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-27T10:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://codepath.io/blog/2012/08/27/ruby-on-redis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever since I found out about the no-sql databases and since they became very popular lately, I wanted to write a blog post about my favourite one: <a href="http://redis.io/">Redis</a>.</p>

<p>What I love so much about it is its simple API. In my honest opinion, one of the very best API&#8217;s that I&#8217;ve found so far.</p>

<p>Also, since it&#8217;s a lightweight and fast key-value store, it&#8217;s specially useful for speeding up slow processes on your system. If things go slow, you should always consider using Redis, if it applies, it will speed things up.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The Ruby gem redis is as easy to use as redis API.
Here&#8217;s a quick look of it&#8217;s usage on Rails. Where there&#8217;s an AR Ranking model, which stores in a sorted set a list of albums to easily get the top [n] albums.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>On config/initializers/redis.rb</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="c1"># Setup the connection to the redis server</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="vg">$redis</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Redis</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">host</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;localhost&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">port</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">6379</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>On app/models/album_ranking.rb</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">AlbumRanking</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="no">ActiveRecord</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="no">Base</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">top_albums</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="vg">$redis</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">zrevrange</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">albums_key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">albums</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">albums</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="vg">$redis</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">multi</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">remove_all_albums</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">albums</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">each</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">|</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">add_album</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">add_album</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">album</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="vg">$redis</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">zadd</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">albums_key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">album</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">downloads_number</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">album</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">remove_album</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">album</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="vg">$redis</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">zrem</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">albums_key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">album</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">remove_all_albums</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="vg">$redis</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">del</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">albums_key</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">albums_key</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s2">&quot;album_ranking:</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">id</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">:albums&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Besides keeping track of sorted elements in a fast way, there are also many other useful ways in which redis could be used.
Here&#8217;s a list of them with a few interesting related resources:</p>

<ul>
<li>Caching resources (in XML or JSON), <a href="http://antirez.com/post/redis-as-LRU-cache.html">LRU caching</a>.</li>
<li>Having data which automatically expires. Another excellent feature needed for LRU caching.</li>
<li>Queues. Highly used by the <a href="https://github.com/defunkt/resque/blob/master/lib/resque/queue.rb#L29">resque gem</a></li>
<li>Keeping highly variable counters (page views, thumbs up, etc). Here&#8217;s a <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/snippets/71/">Flask snippet</a>.</li>
<li>Working with large sets of data (where you don&#8217;t want repeated elements).</li>
</ul>


<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Game Loop]]></title>
    <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/2012/08/03/building-a-game-loop/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-03T17:54:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://codepath.io/blog/2012/08/03/building-a-game-loop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since this is my first codepath post, I wanted to start talking about something we all love: games and the web.</p>

<p>Lately I&#8217;ve been digging into HTML5 game development, with all the fun technologies it involved working with.
Often, I try to make my own simple versions of frameworks, toolkits or game engines, for fun, to learn and for simplicity matters.</p>

<p>The first big problem I ran into when trying to make a simple version of the old pacman game was the game loop.
How are the ghosts supposed to move by themselves? How and when should I notify the canvas that the game changed?</p>

<p>I finally came up with what I believe is an easy and simple way to run a game loop, which I&#8217;ve used ever since for making simplistic games.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This is its shortened version:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Game Loop</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
<span class='line-number'>39</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">pacman</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">GAME_LOOP_MS</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">30</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">Game</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">processing</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kc">false</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">_interval</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">setInterval</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">run</span><span class="p">();</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="nx">bind</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">this</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nx">GAME_LOOP_MS</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">Game</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">prototype</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">doLogic</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">interval</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// Check if player died, move ghosts, update score, etc</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">Game</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">prototype</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">draw</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">interval</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// Draw on canvas. (You probably want to delegate this)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">Game</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">prototype</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">run</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">intervalTime</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">!</span><span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">processing</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">intervalTime</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">GAME_LOOP_MS</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">skippedIntervals</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">processing</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">doLogic</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">intervalTime</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">draw</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">intervalTime</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="c1">// Resetting data</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">skippedIntervals</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">processing</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kc">false</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">else</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">skippedIntervals</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">pacman</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Game</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">Game</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">})(</span><span class="nx">GLOBAL_PACMAN</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This implementation won&#8217;t work for hardcore games, but it does the job with games that need to be updated in really short intervals, and it&#8217;s really simple to understand.
There are also many ways to improve efficiency by using the browsers RequestAnimationFrame function.
Thoughts?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
