<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: leanux | CodePath]]></title>
  <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/categories/leanux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codepath.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-17T16:15:32-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://codepath.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[CodePath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An introduction to Lean UX]]></title>
    <link href="http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/17/an-introduction-to-lean-ux/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-17T13:15:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://codepath.io/blog/2012/09/17/an-introduction-to-lean-ux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/lean-ux/lean-agile-traditional.png"></p>

<p>There's been a lot of buzz around Lean UX this year. Their critics, who call it Lazy UX, state it ignores the insights that only research provides. Those who like it, call it an UX evolution, a faster process that adapts to rapid changing market needs.</p>

<p>To define what Lean UX really is we should focus on what has been left out from Traditional UX. Never changing goals are something hard to picture on a startup. Avoiding time consuming documentation in favor of a greater focus in real life metrics is key in Lean UX.</p>

<p>In traditional UX, research is something we make before the product is conceived, in Lean UX research is not just a step that gets done before or after the product development. Instead, the UX team is constantly defining user needs based on user behavior.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The prototype now becomes your documentation. It is 'the Spec.' Very little if anything more is needed</p><footer><strong>Jeff Gothelf</strong> <cite><a href='http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2011/03/07/lean-ux-getting-out-of-the-deliverables-business/'>Smashing Magazine</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><figure>
  <img src="/images/lean-ux/process_graphic.gif" title="'Credits: Jeff Gothelf'" >
  <figcaption>Credits: Jess Gothelf</figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>When you focus on the experience itself and not on documentation you can speed up the process of prototyping your concept, validating it and learn from user experience. An already known process if you're familiar with Agile methodology. Tools like A/B testing are a great help when you need to test multiple concepts with your users.</p>

<p>Lean UX is a perfect fit for the lean startup movement, regardless of your team's methodology of choice.
On the startup environment it's crucial for teams to be constantly analyzing both the marketplace, and the product itself as pivoting in time can determine the success of the whole operation.</p>

<p>IMHO Lean UX won't replace traditional UX, however, it is definitely an interesting alternative for those who do not have a lot of resources available and need to validate their product/market quickly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
